<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM 'global.entities'>
  %global_entities;
]>

<refentry id='amanda-changers.7'>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>amanda-changers</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
&rmi.source;
&rmi.version;
&rmi.manual.7;
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>amanda-changers</refname>
<refpurpose>Configuring and Using Amanda Changers</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refentryinfo>
&author.dustin;
</refentryinfo>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>Amanda uses changers to arbitrate access to devices
(<manref name="amanda-devices" vol="7"/>)
and data volumes.  Changers provide an abstraction of tape robots, but are used
to manage non-tape media, too.  Amanda communicates with changers through the
Changer API.  This manpage contains a <emphasis>user-level</emphasis> overview
of the API, and does not address details that are only of concern to
developers.  For that purpose, consult the Amanda source code and
http://wiki.zmanda.com.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>TRANSITION</title>

<para>The Amanda Changer API is in transition from version 1.0 - driven by
shell scripts invoked for each changer operation - to version 2.0, composed of
perl objects that can manage parallel access to multiple devices and other
complexity.  When this transition is complete, Amanda devices will, in general,
be specified via a changer, which will provide the necessary device specifier
to access a requested volume.  In the interim, support for the "new" changer
syntax is limited to the experimental
<manref name="amvault" vol="8"/>.
Older applications access the new changer API through a "glue" layer (chg-glue)
which limits the functionality to version-1.0 features, and in many cases still
run the old shell scripts via chg-compat.</para>

<para>The Changer API strives to treat all changers identically, so that
Amanda's behavior is independent of the changer in use.  However, some parts of
Amanda operate differently depending on whether a changer can efficiently
search for a volume with a given label.  This distinction is really only
apparent with tape libraries: those with barcode readers can quickly find a
desired tape, while those without may fall back to an inefficient scan of each
volume.  The capability to perform quick searches is called "fast-search", and
each changer is annotated below to indicate its support.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>SPECIFYING CHANGERS</title>

<para>Changer specifications are strings like
<computeroutput>chg-disk:/my/vtapes</computeroutput>.  The
<computeroutput>chg-</computeroutput> prefix serves to differentiate changers
from devices (see <manref name="amanda-devices" vol="7"/>).  The next portion
(<computeroutput>disk</computeroutput>, in this case) identifies the particular
changer driver to use, and everything that follows the
<computeroutput>:</computeroutput> is interpreted by the driver.  Note that the
<computeroutput>:</computeroutput> character is required, even when nothing
follows it.  This is an easy way to distinguish new changer specifications from
old.</para>

<para>A name which does not match this pattern, but which matches an old
changer script (e.g., <computeroutput>chg-zd-mtx</computeroutput>), invokes the
backward-compatibility changer driver as e.g.,
<computeroutput>chg-compat:chg-zd-mtx</computeroutput>.  If the name does not
match an old changer, then it is treated as an Amanda device, and is wrapped by
the single-device changer, e.g.,
<computeroutput>chg-single:tape:/dev/rmt/0</computeroutput>.</para>

<para>Changers which require additional parameters can also be described in
&amconf; with "changer" sections.  Such a changer defininition creates a
changer "alias", in this case named <emphasis>hp-robot</emphasis>, which can
then be named where an application expects a changer - for example, the target
of the <command>amvault</command> command or in a global
<command>tpchanger</command> parameter.</para>

<refsect2><title>CONFIGURATION</title>

<para>The preferred method of specifying configuration for a changer is as a
"changer" section in &amconf;.  The <emphasis>tapedev</emphasis> parameter
then indicates, by name, the changer that will be used by default by most
Amanda programs.  For example:
<programlisting>
define changer hp-robot {
    tapedev "chg-robot:/dev/sg1"
    property "tape-device" "0=tape:/dev/nst0"
    property append "tape-device" "1=tape:/dev/nst0"
    device_property "BLOCK_SIZE" "512k"
}
# ...
tapedev "hp-robot"
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>Several changer drivers accept <emphasis>changer properties</emphasis> which
control the behavior of the changer.  These properties must be specified in a
changer definition, as in the <emphasis>hp-robot</emphasis> example, above.</para>

<para>Devices, too, can take properties to control their behavior (see <manref
name="amanda-devices" vol="7" />).  Device properties can come from four
places: implicit device properties (from tapetype parameters), global device
properties (from global <emphasis>device_property</emphasis> parameters),
properties in device definitions, and properties in changer definitions.
Properties are applied in this order, with later properties taking
priority.</para>

<para>There are only three implicit properties:
<emphasis>MAX_VOLUME_USAGE</emphasis> is set based on the tapetype
<emphasis>length</emphasis> parameter, <emphasis>READ_BLOCK_SIZE</emphasis> is
set if <emphasis>readblocksize</emphasis> is set, and
<emphasis>BLOCK_SIZE</emphasis> is set based on the
<emphasis>blocksize</emphasis> parameter.</para>

<para>Global device properties always apply.  If the changer specifies a device
by alias, then device properties from the definition apply.  If the changer is
specified by an alias, then properties from that definition applied.</para>

</refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>CHANGER DRIVERS</title>

<para>This section lists the changer drivers included with Amanda, and basic instructions for using them.  For complete How-To information, consult the Amanda wiki at http://wiki.zmanda.com.</para>

<refsect2><title>chg-disk:VTAPEROOT (new)</title>
<programlisting>
tpchanger "chg-disk:/u01/vtapes"
</programlisting>

<para>This changer driver replaces the old <command>chg-disk</command>,
supporting parallel access to vtapes stored in directories named
<computeroutput>slotN</computeroutput> in the directory specified after
<computeroutput>chg-disk:</computeroutput>.  It does so by creating numbered
"drives" so that simultaneous processes can access distinct slots.  This changer is fast-search capable.</para>

<para>The current slot can be accessed using the device name
<computeroutput>file:VTAPEROOT</computeroutput>. This is useful for the <manref
name="amrestore" vol="8" /> command line.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-disk (old)</title>
<programlisting>
tapedev "file:/u01/vtapes"
tpchanger "chg-disk"
changerfile "chg-disk.conf"     # optional file
</programlisting>

<para>This changer script supports sequential access to vtapes stored in
directories named <computeroutput>slotN</computeroutput> in the directory
specified by the <emphasis>tapedev</emphasis> parameter.
The configuration file parameter is:
<programlisting>
LASTSLOT=number    # The number of slots, default to tapecycle setting.
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>This changer is not fast-search capable.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-multi</title>
<programlisting>
tpchanger "chg-multi"
changerfile "chg-multi-state"
</programlisting>

<para>This script simply round-robins a number of distinct device names, as
specified in its configuration file.  It is useful when all volumes for a
configuration have different device names -- for example, with S3 devices.
The <emphasis>changerfile</emphasis> need not exist; it is used as a prefix
for filenames of state files.
</para>

<para>This changer is not fast-search capable.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-manual</title>
<programlisting>
tpchanger "chg-manual"
changerfile "chg-manual.conf"
</programlisting>

<para>This script simply provides distinct device names in a round-robin
fashion, as specified in its configuration file.  It is useful when all volumes
for a configuration have different device names -- for example, with S3
devices.  The configuration file parameters are (as listed in the script):
<programlisting>
resend_mail=900       # resend mail every __ seconds
timeout_mail=604800   # time out after this many seconds (default 7 days)
request="[type]"      # How to request a new tape (default "tty_email")
  request="tty"       # Use the tty to ask the user to change tape.
                      # Can't be use by cron
  request="email"     # Send an email to ask the user to change tape.
  request="tty_email" # Use the tty if it exist or send an email.
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>This changer is not fast-search capable.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-zd-mtx</title>
<programlisting>
tpchanger "chg-zd-mtx"
changerdev "/dev/sg0"         # used with 'mtx -f'
changerfile "chg-zd-mtx.conf"
tapedev "tape:/dev/nst0"
</programlisting>

<para>This script interfaces with a tape drive using the Zubkoff/Dandelion
version of mtx.  That's the version that takes a device specifier with the
<command>-f</command> option and has subcommands like
<command>status</command>.  The configuration file parameters are (as listed in
the script itself):
<programlisting>
firstslot=?                 #### First storage slot (element)
lastslot=?                  #### Last storage slot (element)
cleanslot=-1                #### Slot with cleaner tape -- default is "-1"
                            #### Set negative to indicate no cleaner available
driveslot=0                 #### Drive slot number.  Defaults to 0
                            #### Use the 'Data Transfer Element' you want
autoclean=0                 #### Set to '1' or greater to enable
autocleancount=99           #### Number of access before a clean.
havereader=0                #### If you have a barcode reader, set to 1.
offline_before_unload=0     #### Does your robot require an
                            #### 'mt offline' before mtx unload?
poll_drive_ready=NN         #### Time (seconds) between tests to see if
                            #### the tape drive has gone ready (default: 3).
max_drive_wait=NN           #### Maximum time (seconds) to wait for the
                            #### tape drive to become ready (default: 120).
initial_poll_delay=NN       #### initial delay after load before polling for
                            #### readiness
slotinfofile=FILENAME       #### record slot information to this file, in
                            #### the line-based format "SLOT LABEL\n"
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>This changer is fast-search capable if and only if
<command>havereader</command> is true.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-rait:{CHILD1,CHILD2,..}</title>
<programlisting>
define changer vtape {
    tpcanger "chg-disk:/path/to/vtape"
}
define changer robot {
    tpchanger "chg-robot:/dev/sg0"
    tapedev "tape:/dev/nst0"
}
tpchanger "chg-rait:{vtape,robot}"
</programlisting>

<para>This changer script constructs RAIT devices out of the devices provided by several "sub-changers".  The sub-changers are specified using the same shell-like syntax as the RAIT device (see
<manref name="amanda-devices" vol="7"/>).</para>

<para>Chg-rait does not require that all of the child changers have the same slot names: compound slot names are created by combining the slot names supplied by the child changers using the same shell-like syntax.  For example, if the child changers return slots "<computeroutput>top</computeroutput>", "<computeroutput>strange</computeroutput>", and "<computeroutput>3</computeroutput>", then the RAIT changer will return "<computeroutput>{top,strange,3}</computeroutput>".  This makes it possible to, for example, mirror data on tapes in slots 1-10 to tapes in slots 11-20 of the same robot, using two <command>chg-zd-mtx</command> child changers (and, naturally, two tape drives).  In this arrangement, the first slot would be named <computeroutput>{1,11}</computeroutput>.</para>

<para>As a convenience to the user, the RAIT changer will also accept un-braced slot names, and supply the same name to each child changer. Thus with a 4-device RAIT changer, "<computeroutput>17</computeroutput>" is equivalent to "<computeroutput>{17,17,17,17}</computeroutput>".</para>

<para>This changer is fast-search capable only if all of its child changers are fast-search capable.</para>

<note>The old chg-rait script is no longer supported nor shipped with Amanda, although the old script will continue to function via <command>chg-compat</command>, giving users time to upgrade their configuration.
</note><!-- previous newline is important -->

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-null:</title>
<programlisting>
tpchanger "chg-null:"
</programlisting>

<para>This changer always provides the device "null:".  It is sometimes useful in conjunction with <command>chg-rait:</command>.</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>chg-robot:DEVICE</title>
<programlisting>
define changer robot {
    tpchanger "chg-robot:/dev/sg0"
    property "tape-device" "0=tape:/dev/rmt/0" "1=tape:/dev/rmt/1"
    property "eject-before-unload" "yes"
    property "use-slots" "1-5,11-20"
}
tpchanger "robot"
</programlisting>

<para>This changer drives a robotic tape library using the operating system's
<command>mtx</command> command.  It replaces the ancient
<command>chg-zd-mtx</command> script.  The changer uses all of the information
available to operate as efficiently as possible.  Even without a barcode
reader, the changer can usually load a tape immediately, without resorting to a
sequential scan of many tapes.  It is capable of sharing state across multiple
Amanda configurations, avoiding conflicts and optimally tracking the contents
of the library.</para>

<para>This changer does not accept a <command>changerdev</command> parameter,
but the <command>changerfile</command> parameter can be used to specify a
filename at which it should store its state.  Ordinarily, this state is stored
in a file named after the changer device under
<emphasis>$localstatedir/lib/amanda</emphasis>, e.g.,
<command>/var/lib/amanda/chg-robot-dev-sg0</command>.  There should be a single
such statefile for each distinct tape library attached to the Amanda server, even
if multiple Amanda configurations reference that library.</para>

<para>With a barcode reader present, it is possible for
<command>chg-robot</command> to track the state of the library reliably, even
recognizing tapes that are removed and later re-inserted (by remembering their
barcodes).  Without barcodes, the changer can still remember the slot in which
it last saw the tape with a particular label, although this information can
become stale if the tapes are rearranged by an operator.  In any case, the
changer will never "hunt" for a tape by repeatedly loading slots and checking
labels.  If the changer's state is inaccurate, use the
<manref name="amtape" vol="8" /> subcommand <command>update</command>.</para>

<para>This changer is fast-search capable even without a barcode reader.  For
such libraries, it is the responsibility of the operator to
<command>update</command> the changer when tapes are added to or removed from
the library.</para>

<refsect3><title>Special Operations</title>

<para>A number of special operations are available for <command>chg-robot</command> via
<manref name="amtape" vol="8" /> subcommands.</para>

<para>The <command>reset</command> subcommand will change the current slot to
the first available slot, but does not erase any stored state maintained by the
changer.</para>

<para>The <command>eject</command> subcommand will unload the volume in the
given drive, ejecting first if the changer properties dictate.  Note that,
despite the subcommand name, the changer attempts to avoid the state where a
volume has been ejected from the drive but not unloaded back to a storage
slot.</para>

<para>The <command>clean</command> subcommand is not yet implemented.</para>

<para>The <command>update</command> subcommand instructs the changer to update
its state database.  Given no arguments, the changer will scan all available
slots, loading each tape and reading its label.  Especially for large libraries,
this can take a long time.  If only a few slots have changed, they can be listed
on the command line:
<programlisting>
amtape CONFIG update 1-3,9
</programlisting>
In this case, the changer will only scan the stated slots.  Finally, the changer
will not scan at all if it is given the tape label for the slot:
<programlisting>
amtape CONFIG update 2=DailySet-028
</programlisting>
In this case, the changer updates its state to indicate that
<computeroutput>DailySet-028</computeroutput> is in slot 2, without trying to
load the tape.
</para>

</refsect3>

<refsect3><title>Properties</title>
<!-- PLEASE KEEP THIS LIST IN ALPHABETICAL ORDER -->

<variablelist>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>DRIVE-CHOICE</term><listitem>
This property controls the algorithm used to select a drive in which to load a
tape.  If set to the default ("lru"), the changer attempts to use the least
recently used drive, resulting in a round-robin behavior.  The "firstavail"
algorithm selects the first available drive, thus preferring the first drive
specified via the TAPE-DEVICE property.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>EJECT-BEFORE-UNLOAD</term><listitem>
Set this boolean property to true if the library requires an
<command>offline</command> operation be performed on the tape drive before it
can be unloaded.  If set, then <command>mt</command> will be invoked to
perform this operation.  Most libraries do not require this workaround.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>EJECT-DELAY</term><listitem>
This is the time between ejecting a tape and unloading the volume to a storage slot, and
defaults to 0 seconds.  It is only used if EJECT-BEFORE-UNLOAD is true.  See "Timing", below.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>FAST-SEARCH</term><listitem>
This boolean property indicates whether the changer advertises the ability to find
volumes without sequential scanning.  The traditional taperscan algorithm alters its
behavior based on this flag, so it is sometimes necessary to adjust it, although the
changer will always search for a desired tape using the most efficient means
available.  The default value is true.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>IGNORE-BARCODES</term><listitem>
If this boolean property is true, then chg-robot will ignore any barcode information
that the library provides.  This property is probably only useful when the library
returns incorrect barcodes, for example due to a malfunction in the barcode reader.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>LOAD-POLL</term><listitem>
<para>This property specifies the timing of Amanda's polling for the tape drive to
be ready after loading a new tape.  See "Timing", below.</para>

<para>The script "polls" by trying to open the tape device repeatedly until no
error is encountered.  The property specifies the time to wait before the first
poll (D), the frequency at which to poll and retry on errors (P); and the time
after which it should give up (U).  The format is
<programlisting>
"D [poll P [until U]]"
</programlisting>
For a simple delay with no polling, use e.g.,
<programlisting>
property "load-poll" "13s"
</programlisting>
To delay and then poll, use e.g.,
<programlisting>
property "load-poll" "13s poll 5s"
</programlisting>
and to add a maximum total time, use e.g.,
<programlisting>
property "load-poll" "0s poll 5s until 2m"
</programlisting>
The default value is <command>"0s poll 3s until 2m"</command>.
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>MT</term><listitem>
The path to the 'mt' binary.  Note that this is only used for ejecting volumes.
The default value is defined at compile time.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>MTX</term><listitem>
The path to the 'mtx' binary.  The default value is defined at compile time.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>STATUS-INTERVAL</term><listitem>
This is the minimum time between invocations of <command>mtx status</command>
to determine the state of the changer library.  The default value, 2 seconds,
avoids back-to-back status invocations but ensures that the metadata is up to
date.  For operating systems or libraries where the <command>mtx
status</command> takes a considerable time to complete, this value should be
increased.  See "Timing", below.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>TAPE-DEVICE</term><listitem>
This property describes the correspondance of drive numbers in the library to
Amanda devices, in the format <emphasis>DRIVE=DEVICE</emphasis>.  The property
can be specified multiple times to describe multiple devices.  The device will
usually be a tape device name starting with <command>tape:</command>, but may
also refer to a device alias (see <manref name="amanda-devices" vol="7"/>). As
a shortcut, if the <command>tapedev</command> parameter is specified in the
changer definition, then it is assumed to be the device name for drive 0.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>UNLOAD-DELAY</term><listitem>
This specifies the minimum time between an unload operation any any subsequent
operation.  The default value is 0 seconds.  See "Timing", below.
</listitem></varlistentry>
<!-- ==== -->
<varlistentry><term>USE-SLOTS</term><listitem>
This property, if specifies, enumerates the slots to which this changer should
limit itself.  The slots are specified as a comma-separated list of ranges,
e.g., "1-5,11-15,19,22".  The property can be specified more than once, and
the resulting sets will be combined.  The changer will refuse to load tapes
not found in these slots, except for import/export purposes.
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect3>

<refsect3><title>Timing</title>

<para>Tape libraries are fickle, and in many cases will report that an
operation is complete when it is still in progress.  Chg-robot takes several
timing-related properties to accomodate such behavior.</para>

<para>A typical sequence of operations performed during a load are: get library
status, eject a tape, unload the tape back to a storage slot, load a new tape,
and read the label on that tape to ensure the drive is ready.</para>

<para>On most systems, the library status check is nearly instantaneous -- the
changer library provides its cached state to the host without initiating any
robot motion.  In order to keep its metadata up-to-date, chg-robot runs this
command very frequently, but this frequency can be reduced (at the cost of
potentially stale metadata) by setting the STATUS-INTERVAL property to a larger
value.</para>

<para>Some tape libraries do not integrate the eject operation (performed by
the embedded tape drive) with the unload operation (performed by the library
robot), and can actually cause physical damage by attempting to remove the tape
before the ejection is complete.  For such changers, set the EJECT-DELAY
property to allow enough time for the eject to complete.</para>

<para>Once a tape is unloaded, if the library needs time to "quiesce" before
processing another command, add that time to the UNLOAD-DELAY parameter.  No
other operations will be performed on the library until this delay has
elapsed.</para>

<para>Once a tape has been loaded, chg-robot waits until the drive is ready before
allowing Amanda to use the volume, as described for LOAD-POLL, above.</para>

<para>Each of the times specified in these properties may be given as integers
with the optional suffix <command>s</command> for seconds (the default) or
<command>m</command> for minutes.</para>

</refsect3>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Unmaintained Changers</title>

<para>Amanda has many other changer scripts and programs beyond those described
here (see the <computeroutput>changer-src/</computeroutput> in the source
directory), but most of these scripts are unmaintained and undocumented, and
will be removed when the new changer API is fully implemented.</para>

</refsect2>

</refsect1>

<seealso>
<manref name="amanda.conf" vol="5"/>,
<manref name="amanda-devices" vol="7"/>,
</seealso>


</refentry>
