<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM '../entities/global.entities'>
  %global_entities;
]>

<refentry id='amanda-taperscan.7'>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>amanda-taperscan</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
&rmi.source;
&rmi.version;
&rmi.manual.7;
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>amanda-taperscan</refname>
<refpurpose>Amanda Taperscan Algorithms</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refentryinfo>
&author.dustin;
</refentryinfo>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>Amanda uses a <emphasis>taperscan algorithm</emphasis> to select volumes
on which to store dumps.  Historically Amanda has provided only one, fairly
complex taperscan algorithm, but this algorithm did not suit the needs of all
users.  Now Amanda offers a wide array of algorithms to suit varied needs.
Adding new algorithms is not difficult.</para>

<para>The taperscan algorithm is specified with the <emphasis
remap='B'>taperscan</emphasis> parameter, which has a default value of
<emphasis remap='B'>traditional</emphasis>.</para>

<para>Taperscan algorithms are implemented as perl packages with the prefix
<filename>Amanda::Taper::Scan::</filename>.  See the perl documentation for
<filename>Amanda::Taper::Scan</filename> for more information.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>TAPERSCAN ALGORITHMS</title>

<para>In general, these volumes will only select reusable volumes.  These are
volumes which are listed in the &tapelist; with the <emphasis>reuse</emphasis>
flag, and which are not among the <emphasis>tapecycle-1</emphasis> most recent
volumes in the list.  Put another way, reusable volumes do not contain data
that must be retained.  Note that if fewer than
<emphasis>tapecycle-1</emphasis> volumes have been written then there are no
reusable volumes.  Newly labeled volumes (volumes that have been labeled with
&amlabel; but never used) are considered reusable.</para>

<para>Many of these algorithms look for the oldest reusable volume.  In most
cases, this is the best volume to overwrite, as the data it contains is older
than that on any other volume.  If there are no reusable volumes, then there is
no oldest reusable volume.
</para>

<refsect2><title>traditional</title>

<para>This algorithm duplicates Amanda's historical behavior, and it operates
in two stages.</para>

<para>First, if there is an oldest reusable volume and if the changer supports
"fast" searches, then the algorithm uses the changer to search for that volume.
Newly labeled volumes are not considered when calculating the oldest reusable
volume.  Consequently, this taperscan algorithm prefers volumes which have been
used before to newly-labeled volumes when a fast-searchable changer is in
use.</para>

<para>Second, if there is no oldest reusable volume, or if that volume is not
available in the changer, then the algorithm begins a sequential scan of the
changer, starting at the current slot.  It selects the first suitable volume it
finds: a reusable volume (perhaps newly-labeled) or, if
<emphasis>label_new_tapes</emphasis> is true, a blank volume.</para>

<note>This algorithm shows an undue preference for volumes already containing
data, by omitting newly-labeled volumes from its first stage.  Historically,
many &A; changer scripts were not fast-searchable (including
<emphasis>chg-multi</emphasis>, <emphasis>chg-disk</emphasis> and, if
<emphasis>havereader=0</emphasis>, <emphasis>chg-zd-mtx</emphasis>), and thus
skipped the first stage, allowing new volumes to find their way into the tape
cycle.  New changers are almost all fast-searchable, so both stages of the
algorithm are used and new tapes may be unexpectedly excluded.  If this causes
an undesirable change in behavior, consider one of the other taperscan
algorithms.</note>

</refsect2>

</refsect1>

<seealso>
<manref name="amanda.conf" vol="5"/>,
<manref name="tapelist" vol="5"/>,
<manref name="amanda-changers" vol="7"/>,
</seealso>

</refentry>

