<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM '../entities/global.entities'>
  %global_entities;
]>

<refentry id='amanda-compatibility.7'>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>amanda-compatibility</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
&rmi.source;
&rmi.version;
&rmi.manual.7;
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>amanda-compatibility</refname>
<refpurpose>Compatibility between Amanda versions</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refentryinfo>
&author.dustin;
</refentryinfo>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1><title>NETWORK COMPATIBILITY</title>

<para>Amanda has used several on-the-wire protocols to communicate between the
server and backup clients, and not all of them have been compatible.</para>

<para>Versions of Amanda prior to about 2.3 used a different protocol which is
not compatible. 2.3 is very old so this is not of general interest.</para>

<para>The Amanda 2.4 series all use the same protocol. This protocol has
support for extensibility. Generally upgrading clients or servers along the 2.4
branch does not cause difficulty.</para>

<para>Amanda 2.5.0 uses the same protocol as 2.4. One can use a 2.5.0 server
with 2.4 clients and a 2.4 server with 2.5.0 clients.</para>

<para>Kerberos4 authentication in 2.5 is compatible with 2.4. In 2.5, kerberos4
encryption is broken, at least for the server.</para>

<para>Amanda 2.5.1 introduced a new recover protocol. Backup communication
works with any combination of versions, but 2.5.1's amrecover cannot
communicate with an older server. Use oldamrecover on 2.5.1 and higher clients
when communicating with an older server.</para>

<para>Amanda 2.6.0 and later are completely compatible with 2.5.1.</para>

<para>To restore a dump created with the tapesplit_size option using amrecover,
you need at least a 2.5 server and late-2.4 client. (Extracting that backup
using only shell, mt and dd is also possible.)</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>UPGRADES</title>

The recommended course for Amanda upgrades is to upgrade the server first, and
test backups and restores before upgrading clients.  Consult the changes
described below for the relevant span of versions to determine what
adjustments, if any, are required.

<refsect2><title>Amanda 2.6.1</title>

<para>There are no incompatible changes in this release, but consider switching
to some of the new applications instead of the old GNUTAR and DUMP
programs.</para>

<para>The following configuration configration keywords are deprecated and will
be removed in the next release:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>tapebufs</computeroutput> - use <computeroutput>device-output-buffer-size</computeroutput> instead</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>rawtapedev</computeroutput> - use <computeroutput>tapedev</computeroutput> instead</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>file-pad</computeroutput> - this is no longer optional, and all files are padded</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Amanda 2.6.0</title>

<para><filename>amverify</filename> and <filename>amverifyrun</filename> are removed and replaced with <manref name="amcheckdump" vol="8" />.  Both <filename>amdd</filename> and <filename>ammt</filename> are removed.</para>

<para>Some Amanda files are now installed in new <filename>amanda/</filename>
subdirectories: libraries are now installed in
<filename>$libdir/amanda</filename> and internal programs are now installed in
<filename>$libexecdir/amanda</filename>.</para>

<para> The amandates file, previously at <filename>/etc/amandates</filename>,
is now at <filename>$localstatedir/amanda/amandates</filename>.  You may want
to move your existing <filename>/etc/amandates</filename> when you upgrade
Amanda.</para>

<para>GLib is now required to build and run Amanda.</para>

</refsect2>

</refsect1>

<seealso>
<manref name="amanda.conf" vol="5"/>,
</seealso>


</refentry>
