<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM '../entities/global.entities'>
  %global_entities;
]>

<refentry id='amzfs-holdsend.8'>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>amzfs-holdsend</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
&rmi.source;
&rmi.version;
&rmi.manual.8;
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>amzfs-holdsend</refname>
<refpurpose>Amanda Application for backup of
ZFS externally-created snapshots</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refentryinfo>
<author><personname>Chapman Flack</personname></author>
</refentryinfo>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>Amzfs-holdsend is an Amanda Application API script. It should not be run
by users directly. It can backup and restore ZFS filesystems opaquely
(that is, as a whole, with no option to restore just some entries),
using <command>zfs send</command> <emphasis>replication streams</emphasis>
based on snapshots created by other means.</para>

<refsect2><title>ZFS backup approaches compared</title>

<para>ZFS is a sophisticated filesystem manager that lends itself to several
backup approaches depending on need (and different approaches can be used
on different datasets in the same pool). For two other approaches available
in Amanda, see <manref name="amzfs-sendrecv" vol="8"/> and
<manref name="amzfs-snapshot" vol="8"/>.</para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm><command>amzfs-snapshot</command></glossterm>
<glossdef><para>
A script that can be combined with a conventional file-based archiving
application, such as <manref name="amgtar" vol="8"/>, when the ability
to restore individual files will be important. The script creates a new
ZFS snapshot, the archiver copies files from the snapshot in the usual
way (but without the inefficient side effect of clobbering access times,
because the snapshot is read-only), and then the script destroys the snapshot.
</para><para>
Individual files can be recovered in the usual way, though how much
advanced metadata gets preserved will depend on what
the archiving tool supports. Strictly ZFS-specific features "outside"
the filesystem, such as historical snapshots and filesystem properties,
are not preserved.
</para></glossdef></glossentry>
<glossentry><glossterm><command>amzfs-sendrecv</command></glossterm>
<glossdef><para>
An application that uses <command>zfs send</command> to faithfully
preserve the contents of a single ZFS filesystem at a single point
in time. It creates a new snapshot as of the time it is executed,
and can leave the snapshot in place when done so that a future run
can be incremental. An incremental run advances the filesystem contents
to the just-created new snapshot, but does not preserve intermediate
snapshots along the way.
</para></glossdef></glossentry>
<glossentry><glossterm><command>amzfs-holdsend</command></glossterm>
<glossdef><para>
<emphasis>This application</emphasis>: uses the <emphasis>replication
stream</emphasis> feature of <command>zfs send</command> to preserve
a ZFS filesystem or volume and any descendants. This application does
not create or destroy snapshots on its own, but selects recent snapshots
assumed to be created by other means, such as a scheduler that may take
snapshots at regular intervals. Existing historical snapshots are preserved
in the backup.
</para></glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>
In general, approaches that use a conventional archiver have the advantage
that individual files are easily restored when needed, and (typically, at
least) a few disadvantages: they may not preserve all advanced metadata
(ACLs, security contexts, etc.) supported by the filesystem, identification
of changed files for incremental backup may require traversing the whole
filesystem making fallible comparisons, and increments may grow larger than
necessary by including entire files that have seen but small changes.
</para>

<para>
This application, as well as <command>amzfs-sendrecv</command>, take
the complementary approach. While they do not provide
for easy recovery of individual files, they faithfully preserve all of the
filesystems' contents and metadata, identify all changed objects in an
increment without relying on fallible checks, and require only the size
of changed data, even with small changes to large files.
</para>

<para>
In an environment where nothing else is creating snapshots, and there is no
desire to preserve anything but the most recent state at each backup,
<command>amzfs-sendrecv</command> may be a simple solution, as it takes care
of creating its own snapshot on each backup run.
</para>

<para>
If snapshots are being created by other means, such as on a frequent schedule
between backups, or if intermediate snapshots between scheduled backups should
all be preserved, <command>amzfs-holdsend</command> fits the bill. It does not
add to or delete from the existing snapshots, but preserves them as they are.
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Multiple datasets in one DLE</title>

<para>
ZFS arranges datasets (its generic term for both filesystems and
block-device-like volumes) in a tree. The tree structure does not have
to mirror the desired layout of filesystem mount points, but can be used
to group datasets meant to be similar in other ways, compression settings
for example, or datasets to be backed up together.
</para>

<para>
For <command>amzfs-holdsend</command>, the <emphasis>disk</emphasis> or
<emphasis>device</emphasis> given in a disk-list entry names a subtree of
datasets to back up. It must always be a ZFS-style dataset name, not a
mountpoint, to make clear that it points into the ZFS namespace hierarchy
rather than the filesystem namespace, and the backup will include that dataset
and any others descended from it in the ZFS tree.
</para>

<para>
For a subtree to be backed up at once by <command>amzfs-holdsend</command>,
certain conditions must hold. For a full (level 0) backup, there must be at
least one snapshot name that is present on every dataset in the subtree. An easy
way to ensure that is to use <code>zfs snapshot -r ...</code> to create
snapshots with identical names on a dataset and all its descendants in one
command. However, the stream generation does not depend on that: there is no
requirement that the same-named snapshots were created together, or even
closely in time; they simply have to exist. If <command>amzfs-holdsend</command>
will not back up a certain subtree because no common snapshot name can be found,
if there is a snapshot name that is present in most of the datasets, the remedy
can be as simple as creating snapshots by that name in the datasets lacking it.
When <command>amzfs-holdsend</command> can identify one or more snapshot names
present in the named dataset and all descendants, it will use the latest of
those for a level-0 backup.
</para>

<note><para>
You could be sly and create some snapshots with matching names
everywhere in the subtree, but not always in the same order. When
<command>amzfs-holdsend</command> picks the "latest" of them, it uses the
one that is latest in the topmost dataset, the one that the DLE names.
</para></note>

<para>
For an <emphasis>incremental</emphasis> backup to be produced, the snapshots
used for the next lower backup level must still be present, and must still all
have the same name. (If any has been renamed, so must they all.) For a
useful backup, there must also be some newer snapshots with their own common
name throughout the subtree; again, the "latest" will be used as the new end
point for the incremental backup.
</para>

<note><para>
You could be sly again and arrange for a later snapshot in some
datasets to match the name of a snapshot that came earlier than the
prior-level backup snapshot in some other datasets in the same subtree.
You won't get away with it, however.
</para></note>

<para>
If no new snapshot has been created since the last backup, a (trivial)
incremental backup can still be created, from the last-used snapshot
to itself. There are warnings from <command>zfs send</command> in that
case, but it successfully produces a restorable increment with no
filesystem-content changes. It will include the latest values of any
changed ZFS properties.
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Holds on snapshots</title>

<para>
After a backup, <command>amzfs-holdsend</command> places
<command>zfs hold</command> tags on the snapshots that must be
kept around for future increments. The tags have a recognizable prefix
followed by the backup level, and serve two purposes. For this application,
they record which backup levels used which snapshots; for ZFS itself, they
protect the snapshots from inadvertent deletion.
</para>

<para>
So that a dataset or subtree can belong to more than one DLE (to back up
to more than one media series, or onsite/offsite, etc.), HOLDTAGPREFIX
is a property that can be set in a DLE or dumptype. With the different
DLEs using different prefixes, the hold tags they generate can coexist.
</para>

<note><para>
As <command>amzfs-holdsend</command> releases some holds and places others
when a backup completes, there can be a moment when it has no holds on any
of the snapshots needed for future increments. That should not be a problem,
unless many snapshots have been queued up for destruction with
<command>zfs destroy -d</command>, in which case they could all vanish
before a new hold can be placed, making that a risky practice.
</para></note>

<note><para>
When attempts to destroy a filesystem or snapshot are met with
"snapshot is busy" complaints from ZFS, the holds are doing their job.
When destroying the filesystem or snapshot really is what you want to do,
manually-issued <command>zfs release</command> commands (after sober
reflection) can remove the conflicting holds.
</para></note>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Permissions needed</title>

<para>
Because <command>amzfs-holdsend</command> only needs to create and release
holds and invoke <command>zfs send</command>, it will work with just those
three ZFS permissions delegated to the Amanda backup user:
</para>

<programlisting>
  zfs allow -u amandabackup hold,send,release filesystem
</programlisting>

<para>
Additional permissions are needed for recovery, but <command>amrecover</command>
is typically run as superuser, so there is no need to grant more permissions
to the backup user.
</para>

<para>
On a platform that lacks <command>zfs allow</command> support, it may be
necessary to use <command>pfexec</command>, <command>sudo</command>, or a
custom setuid wrapper for the <command>zfs</command> command.
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2><title>Estimate method</title>

The estimate methods CLIENT and CALCSIZE are supported. CALCSIZE is both
fast and accurate, but works only on platforms that support
<command>zfs send -nvP</command> as found in OpenZFS. CLIENT is slower,
but works on platforms without that support.

</refsect2>

</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>PROPERTIES</title>

<para>This section lists the properties that control amzfs-holdsend's
functionality.
See <manref name="amanda-applications" vol="7"/>
for information on application properties and how they are configured.
</para>

<!-- PLEASE KEEP THIS LIST IN ALPHABETICAL ORDER -->
<variablelist>
 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>HOLDTAGPREFIX</term><listitem>
All hold tags placed by this application on snapshots will consist of
this prefix, a single space, and a number representing the backup level.
If one ZFS dataset or subtree is to participate in more than one DLE
(for different backup media series, onsite/offsite, etc.), this property
can be used to set distinct prefixes for the DLEs, so the holds they create
do not interfere. The default is the string "org.amanda holdsend".
</listitem></varlistentry>

 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>ZFSEXECUTABLE</term><listitem>
Full path to the <command>zfs</command> executable on the client system.
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<refsect2><title>Properties specific to recovery</title>

<para>The properties in this section apply to recovery only.
They can be set using the <command>setproperty</command> command within
an <manref name="amrecover" vol="8"/> session.
</para>

<!-- PLEASE KEEP THIS LIST IN ALPHABETICAL ORDER -->
<variablelist>
 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>DATASET</term><listitem>
The ZFS name under which to recover the data. Because ZFS recovery involves
whole filesystems at a time, to reduce the risk of clobbering wanted filesystems
by mistake, this property does <emphasis>not</emphasis> default to the device
named in the DLE; it must be set explicitly with <command>setproperty</command>
ahead of an <command>extract</command> within <command>amrecover</command>.
There is no prohibition on setting it the same as the device in the DLE if
desired, though it is also easy to set it to a different name and rename it
after successful recovery.
</listitem></varlistentry>

 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>DESTRUCTIVE</term><listitem>
Controls whether the <option>-F</option> is given to
<command>zfs receive</command> when restoring increments (it will always be
used when restoring the level 0 base, regardless of this property).
The default is true, meaning descendant datasets and snapshots that
disappear in a later increment will be destroyed as that increment is replayed,
so the final result matches the original. This property can be set to false,
if desired, so that destructions of datasets or snapshots will not be replayed.
</listitem></varlistentry>

 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>EXCLUDEPROPERTY</term><listitem>
Takes one or more ZFS dataset property names, which will not be applied from
the recovered backup stream (so the values of those properties in the received
dataset will be defaulted or inherited in the usual way, as if no value had
been saved in the backup stream.
Not every platform supports the <option>-x</option> to
<command>zfs receive</command>; use of this property on platforms that do not
will cause recovery to fail.
</listitem></varlistentry>

 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>OVERRIDEPROPERTY</term><listitem>
Takes one or more values of the form
<token>property</token><code>=</code><token>value</token>, which will be
applied in the received dataset inplace of values saved in the backup stream.
Not every platform supports the <option>-o</option> to
<command>zfs receive</command>; use of this property on platforms that do not
will cause recovery to fail.
</listitem></varlistentry>

 <!-- ==== -->
 <varlistentry><term>UNMOUNTED</term><listitem>
Controls whether the <option>u</option> is given to
<command>zfs receive</command> to suppress automatic mounting of
datasets received.
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>EXAMPLE</title>
<para>
<programlisting>
  define application-tool app_amzfsholdsend {
    plugin "amzfs-holdsend"
  }
</programlisting>
A dumptype using this application might look like:
<programlisting>
  define dumptype amzfshold {
    global
    program "APPLICATION"
    application "app_amzfsholdsend"
  }
</programlisting>
Note that the <emphasis>program</emphasis> parameter must be set to
<emphasis>"APPLICATION"</emphasis> to use the <emphasis>application</emphasis>
parameter.
</para>
</refsect1>

<seealso>
<manref name="amanda.conf" vol="5"/>,
<manref name="amanda-applications" vol="7"/>
<manref name="amrecover" vol="8"/>
</seealso>

</refentry>
