<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM 'global.entities'>
  %global_entities;
]>

<refentry id='tapelist.5'>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>tapelist</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
&rmi.source;
&rmi.version;
&rmi.manual.5;
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>tapelist</refname>
<refpurpose>The list of Amanda volumes in use</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refentryinfo>
&author.jds;
&author.sgw.xml;
&author.dustin;
</refentryinfo>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>The <emphasis remap='I'>tapelist</emphasis> file contains the list of
tapes in active use.  This file is not ordinarily ordinarily edited or examined
manually.  Its format may change, or it may be removed altogether, in future
versions of Amanda.  It contains lines of the form:</para>

<para><programlisting>YYYYMMDD label flags [#comment]
</programlisting></para>

<para>Where
<emphasis remap='I'>YYYYMMDD</emphasis>
is the date the tape was written,
<emphasis remap='I'>label</emphasis>
is a label for the tape as written by
<emphasis remap='B'>amlabel</emphasis>
and
<emphasis remap='I'>flags</emphasis>
is one of "reuse" or "no-reuse" and tells Amanda whether the tape may be reused.
A non-reusable tape will not be overwritten, even if it is older than <emphasis
remap='B'>dumpcycle</emphasis> dumps.  See the
<emphasis remap='B'>reuse</emphasis>
options of
<manref name="amadmin" vol="8"/>.
The optional comment is prefixed with a '#' and continues to the end of the line.  Amanda
will maintain this comment until the tape is overwritten.  Note that comments are not
allowed on blank lines.</para>

<para>The file is sorted such that the most-recently used tape appears on the first line, and the oldest tape appears on the last line.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>Amdump</emphasis>
and
<emphasis remap='B'>amflush</emphasis>
will by default refuse to write to an unlabeled tape, or to a labeled tape that
is considered active or marked "no-reuse".  There must be more tapes in active
rotation (see the
<emphasis remap='B'>tapecycle</emphasis>
option) than there are runs in the backup cycle (see the
<emphasis remap='B'>dumpcycle</emphasis>
option) to prevent overwriting a backup image that would be needed to do a full recovery.</para>
</refsect1>

<seealso>
<manref name="amanda.conf" vol="5"/>
</seealso>

</refentry>
